Ravindra Singh Rawat



Contact

Address: NH-72 Chakrata Road Jhajra, Premnagar Dehradun, Uttarakhand 248007

Phone:

9820793187/9654103288

Email:

ravindrarawat48@gmail.com

Website:

https://sites.google.com/site/ravindras rawat19/

LinkedIn:

https://www.linkedin.com/in/ravindrasingh-rawat-3803b73a/

Githut: https://github.com/rsr1987

Languages

English, Hindi, Spanish Basic Level

Hobbies

Innovating & Motivating Writing, Discussion & Debate on Business Ideas and Challenges

Brief Profile

Mr. Ravindra Singh Rawat enriched with Eight years of work experience. He has Three and half years of Corporate and more than Five years of Academic experience. He has earned his Master's degree from recognized B-School New Delhi Institute of Management in the area of Marketing Management and International Business. He is pursuing his Ph.D. from Uttarakhand Technical University his area of research is Digital Marketing.

He has done various specialization certificate programs in the Contemporary fields of Digital Marketing, Data Science, Entrepreneurship and Business Management from the top Educators of the world name of few 'Entrepreneurship in Emerging Economies' from Harvard Business School, 'Digital Marketing' from University of Illinois 'Search Engine Optimization' from University of California, Davis, 'Virtual Teacher' from University of California, Irvine 'Business Statistics and Analysis' from Rice University, 'Data Science & Al Foundations for Business' from IBM.

He is continuously contributing in research and published one chapter in book titled as "People Management In 21st Century- Practice & Challenges" published under TATA MCRAW on ENTREPRENEURSHIP and others in his area of speaciliatzion.

Career Objective

Looking for a full-time position in Academics and Research where I can utilize my 'Eight and half years' of experience in corporate and academic sectors for the ultimate benefit of my prospective students and organization apart from my personal satisfaction and growth.

Skill Highlights

- Marketing Management
- Advertising and Branding
- Digital Marketing
- Search Engine Optimization
- Artificial Intelligence in Business
- Data Science.
- Professional Communication
- Leadership.

Education

- Ph.D. (Pursuing) enrolled in 2016, from Uttarakhand Technical University in Management.
- PGDM/MBA in 2012 from New Delhi Institute of Management (Accredited by NBA, GOI & Approved by AICTE & AIU) with First Division.
- BBA in 2010 from H. N. B. Gharwal University with First Division.
- **HSC (Science)** in 2004 from S.V.M Inter College Vikasnagar, Dehradun (Uttaranchal Board) with **Second Division**.
- **SSC (Science)** in 2002 S.G.R.R. Inter College Shaspur, Dehradun (Uttaranchal Board) with **First Division**.

PROFESSIONAL CERTIFICATION & SPECIALIZATION PROGRAMS

- 1) Entrepreneurship in Emerging Economies, Harvard University, Harvard School of Business, US.
- 2) Specialization Program in Digital Marketing with 7 Courses, University of Illinois at Urbana Champaign: Marketing in a Digital World, Digital Analytics for Marketing Professionals: Marketing Analytics in Theory, Digital Analytics for Marketing Professionals: Marketing Analytics in Practice Digital Media and Marketing Principle Digital Media and Marketing Strategies, Marketing in an Analog World, Digital Marketing Capstone.
- 3) Specialization Program in Search Engine Optimization (SEO) with 5 Courses, University of California, Davis: Introduction to Search Engine Optimization., Search Engine Optimization Fundamentals. Optimizing a Website for Search., Advanced Content and Social Tactics to Optimize SEO, Website Optimization Client Report Project.
- 4) Project Work Coursera on "Build a Full Website using WordPress".
- 5) Project Work Coursera on "Getting Started in Google Analytics".
- 6) Brand Management: Aligning Business, Brand &Behaviors, University of London, London Business School.
- 7) Specialization Program in Key Technologies for Business Specialization with 3 Courses, IBM: Introduction to Cloud Computing, Introduction to Artificial Intelligence (AI), What is Data Science.
- **8) Specialization Program in Data Science Specialization** with **4 Courses, IBM:** What is Data Science, Tools for Data Science, Data Science **Introduction to** Methodology, Databases and SQL for Data Science
- 9) Specialization Program in IBM AI Foundations for Business Specialization with 3 Courses: Introduction to Artificial Intelligence (AI), What is Data Science, The AI Ladder: A Framework for Deploying AI in your Enterprise
- **10) Specialization Program in Business Statistics and Analysis with 5 Courses, Rice University.** Introduction to Data Analysis Using Excel., Basic Data Descriptors, Statistical Distributions, and Application to Business Decisions., Business Applications of Hypothesis Testing and Confidence Interval Estimation, Linear Regression for Business Statistics., Business Statistics and Analysis Capstone.
- **11)** Specialization Program in **Virtual Teacher** with **5 Courses University of California, Irvine**. Foundations of Virtual Instruction, Emerging Trends & Technologies in the Virtual K-12 Classroom, Advanced Instructional Strategies in the Virtual Classroom, Performance Assessment in the Virtual Classroom, Virtual Teacher Final Project.
- **12)** Communication Strategies for a Virtual Age, University of Toronto.
- 13) Introduction to Public Speaking, University of Washington.
- **14)** Self-Awareness and the Effective Leader, **Rice University**.

RESEARCH PAPERS / CONFERENCES

- 1) A Research Paper on "Role of Social Media in Advertising" is published in JETIR, April 2019 Volume 6, Issue 4 (ISSN -2349-5162) UGC Approved.
- 2) A Research Paper on "Comparative Study Online Advertising and Conventional Advertising Strategies" in JETIR May 2019 Volume 6, Issue 5 (ISSN -2349-55162) UGC Approved.
- 3) A chapter written in Book Titled as "PEOPLE MANAGEMENT IN 21st CENTURY- PRACTICE AND CHALLENGES" published under TATA MCRAW on ENTREPRENEURSHIP, ISBN 13:978-93-5316-121-7 ISBN-10: 93-5316-121-5.

4) Presented research paper on Entrepreneurship, Environment and Sustainable Development: Can it go hand in hand? at one-day International Conference on "People Management and Sustainable Economy: Issues and Challenges for Organizations in 21st Century" - held in New Delhi Institute of Management on 18 March, 2017

FDP/SEMINAR/ CONFERENCE

- 1) Attended Webinar on 3rd Felicitation Ceremony on Teacher's Day organized by Divya Himgiri in collaboration with Commission for Scientific and Technical Terminology, MHRD Government of India, Uttarakhand Department of School Education, Uttarakhand Statutory Education Council, Uttarakhand Technical University, Sridev Suman University, Society for Research and Development in Science Dehradun, Uttarakhand, 5 Sep, 2020.
- 2) Attended Webinar Series on "Advanced Technology as a part of Startup in India" organized by Indrashil University (IU) Gujarat, 18-29 August 2020.
- 3) Attended 2-Days National webinar organized under the aegis of Commission for Scientific and Technical Terminology, Ministry of Education Government of India (New Delhi) and Women Institute of Technology Dehradun, Uttarakhand, 17 18 August 2020.
- 4) Attended National Faculty Development Program on "Case Writing & Case Teaching" organized by Globsyn Business School, Kolkata West Bengal during 7-8 Aug, 2020.
- 5) Acted as Keynote Speaker for MDP organized by Eran Health on "Digital Techniques to Accelerate Business Post Pandemic", 20 Jun, 2020.
- 6) Attended one day National Level Symposium on "Design Thinking in Digital Marketing" organized by Vignan's Foundation Science Technology & Research (Deemed to be University) during 24 May,2020.
- 7) Honored with Certificate of Appreciation for organizing "International Conference on Information Technology and Management for the Sustainable Development ICITMSD-2019)" Jointly organized by Life Way Tech India Uttaranchal University, Uttaranchal Institute of Management, Dehradun during 9-10 Aug, 2019.
- 8) Attended 10-Days Faculty Development Program on "Data Analysis Techniques Using SPSS" organized by Uttaranchal Institute of Management, Uttaranchal University, Dehradun during 22-31 July,2019.
- 9) Certificate Program from IIT Bombay, on LaTeX, Organized by IIT Bombay funded by National Mission on Education through ICT, MHRD, Govt Of India. on 15/ Jan/2019.
- 10) Attended Teachers' Congruence & Faculty Development Program organized by Uttaranchal University in association with The Institute of Company Secretaries of India, Dehradun Chapter under the aegis of LAW COLLEGE DEHRADUN during 16th July, 2018.
- 11) Attended 7-Days FACULTY DEVELOPMENT PROGRAMME on "Innovative Techniques and Magnitude of Teaching Methodology in Higher Education" organized by Uttaranchal University during 16th -22nd July, 2018.
- **12)** Attended course work on Research Methodology organized at **Uttarakhand Technical University**, Dehradun during **26th -30th Dec**, **2017**.
- 13) Attended One-Day National Seminar on "GST" held in Uttaranchal University on 28thNov 2017.
- **14)** Attended **5-Days** Faculty Development Program on "Research Methodology & Data Analysis using SPSS" held in Uttaranchal University on **27th July, 2017**.
- **15)** Attended **6-Days** Faculty Development Program on "Research Methodology" held in Uttaranchal University on 04th -9th December, 2017.

WORK EXPERIENCE IN ACADEMICS

University of Petroleum & Energy Sciences (SoB, SoE, SoCS)

Visiting Faculty

Jan-2020-Till Date (1/2 Year)

Role & Responsibilities:

- Developing course and content for the programs teaching in Blended mode (Online SAP BlackBord Software) and offline Face to Face mode.
- 2) Preparing Course Plan, Lecture Plan as per the credit allotted to the course, updating students on regular basis, conducted various assessment activities and designed online/ offline assessment and evaluation scheme.
- 3) Preparing and Maintaining the records of assessment and evaluation plans as per the guidelines of IQAC compliance.
- **4)** Regular monitoring and mapping of Course Outcome, Program Outcomes, and Program Specific Outcomes for the better delivery and performance of the students.
- 5) Community Building (Interaction and Communication) with the students and making them understand about Technology Tools (Synchronous and Asynchronous) for better delivery.
- 6) Making announcements about various differentiated Instruction (At Risk, High Performing, and Special Needs Students to make them aware about their courses and take immediate actions as per their requirement.

Uttaranchal University Assistant Pro (Faculty of Management & Business Studies)

Assistant Professor July-2015-Jan-2020 (4.5Year)

Role & Responsibilities:

- 1) As Head Cultural Academic Affairs, Conceptualized, Designed various activities and events for the ultimate benefit of the students like International Conference, Academic and Nonacademic Club's activities, Entrepreneurial Events, Social Engagement etc.
- 2) Delivered lectures on subjects like Marketing Management, Consumer Behavior, Fundamentals of Retailing, Marketing Communication and Advertising, Business Communication, Business Laws, and Corporate Laws.
- 3) Have Set University Examination Question Papers for BBA, B. Com (H), LLB and MBA courses in Marketing Communication and Advertising, Marketing Management, Business Laws and Fundamental of Retailing, Consumer Behavior
- 4) Criteria Coordinator for IQAC Criteria -7, "Institutional Values and Best Practices".
- 5) Supervise and guide to the students for their summer training projects and dissertation reports.
- 6) Worked as Associate Editor for university web updates.

WORK EXPERIENCE IN CORPORATES

Asian Business Exhibition & Conference Ltd. Assistant Event Manager (Sep 2013- Jun 2015) (Times Property Exhibition) (Corporate Sales)

(1.8 Year)

Roles and Responsibilities

- Worked as an Assistant Event Manager for Asian Business Exhibition & Conference Ltd. Gurgaon Office. I was responsible strategizing the growth in sales, marketing policies and analyzing prospective clients for the exhibitions.
- 2) To liaison with various corporate houses and sending them invitations for participating in exhibition and conference.
- **3)** To present floor plan and negotiate with the Advertising & Promotional Heads of the company for the exhibitions.
- 4) To finalize the space allocation, documentation, and payment procedure with the exhibitors.
- 5) To create new Paper, Pamphlet, Hoarding Advertisements for the promotion of exhibitions and exhibitors,
- 6) To plan for the Branding & Promotion of exhibitions & exhibitors in Times Property News Paper.
- **7)** To execute appropriate planning, organizing, supervising, directing, and controlling activities in the exhibitions.
- **8)** To make a regular follow up with prospective clients to increase client base as well as to generate higher revenue for the organization.

Indiabulls Securities Limited

Relationship Manage

(Jan2012-Sep2013)

Roles & Responsibilities:

- 1) Worked as a Relationship Manager in Indiabulls Securities Ltd. Gurgaon Sales Head Office. My responsibilities included inter alia ensuring effective analysis of prospects for equity and real estate market to deliver good performance.
- **2)** Acquiring new HNI clients and formulating strategies to increase the client base for equity and real estate markets.
- 3) Dealing with the than existing and prospective clients and update them for best lucrative investment projects in equity and real estate markets.
- **4)** Reviewing regular client portfolio and providing advisory services to them in equity and real estate markets.
- **5)** Approaching clients on a need-based product through strategic financial planning.
- 6) Assessing the portfolio risk, according to the changing market scenario

ACHIEVEMENTS/CO-CURRICULAR /EXTRA-CURRICULAR ACTIVITIES

- 1) Won "AIMA National Management Game 2011" award at Zonal level.
- 2) Topped the college in BBA.
- 3) Participated in 'NDTV TALK-SHOW Money Mantra" on Financial Inclusion.
- 4) Awarded "Best Performer" for archiving, CEO sales target in Indiabulls Securities Ltd.
- 5) Basic Course of Spanish from "ALHAMBRA Institudo de la Cultura y la lengua española".
- 6) Alumnus "Anupam Kher's Actor Prepares Acting School" Juhu Mumbai.
- 7) Evaluating and Analyzing, Segmentation Model of "COCA COLA RED (Right Execution Daily)" from Hindustan Coca Cola Beverages Pvt. Ltd. Nodia Sec-63, in 2011.

PERSONAL INFORMATION

Permanent Address: Village – Jhajra, P. O. - Suddhowala, Dehradun, Uttarakhand 248007.

Father's Name & Occupation: Mr. R. S. Rawat & Bank Accountant.

Nationality: Indian.

Marital Status: Unmarried.

DECLARATION

I hereby declare that the above-mentioned information is correct, up to best of my knowledge and belief. I bear the responsibility for the correctness of the above-mentioned particulars.

Place: Dehradun	Ravindra Singh Rawat
Date: / / .	